<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section>
    <title>TYPO3 Phoenix</title>

    <para>Back in 2005 it was decided to start with a new TYPO3 version that
    should eventually replace the current major version 4. In the long and
    twisted process that followed we had to write a new framework first
    (FLOW3), struggle with the release schedule of PHP6, fight tools not
    supporting PHP namespaces, and come up with good ideas for that
    next-generation CMS we were about to build.</para>

    <para>Now we actually have first releases of TYPO3 Phoenix, as it was
    codenamed back then – and they are probably not what you expected. They
    are sprint releases, following a iteration in our Scrum-based project
    management. As such they are complete releases, doing everything they are
    supposed to do, <emphasis>according to the goals of their
    sprint</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>They are not, releases of TYPO3 5.0, though - as you would probably
    laugh about the feaure set, then...</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>System Overview</title>

    <para>TYPO3 Phoenix is made up of packages and based on the FLOW3
    framework. Most of the packages are part of the FLOW3 base system, TYPO3
    Phoenix consists of a few additional packages, like TYPO3, TypoScript,
    TYPO3CR in which the actual CMS functionality is contained. The templates,
    graphics and content of the demo site are in another package.<figure>
        <title>The TYPO3 Phoenix system structure</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="SystemStructure.png"
                       scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>
  </section>
</chapter>
